# Nelson Simões Ribeiro Jr.

Sorocaba, São Paulo, Brazil



nelsonsrj@hotmail.com



+55 71 98459-6000



linkedin.com/in/nelson-sim%C3%B5es-ribeiroir-77b0a6104

# Summary

\*\* For an English version, contact me or check detailed information that can be found bellow, on the professional experience section.

Olá! Uma das minhas características mais marcantes é minha objetividade, então vamos ao assunto, agradeço seu interesse na minha vida profissional, seja bem-vindo!

Minha carreira sempre foi marcada por grandes mudanças, exigindo adaptação rápida a assuntos que antes eram desconhecidos para mim. Desde minhas primeiras experiências como desenvolvedor, Adm. de banco de dados, e depois como líder de equipe no final dos anos 90 até meus recentes trabalhos como especialista em continuidade de negócios, Project Owner e ScrumMaster em uma equipe de qualidade e processos, tive chance de tentar e conhecer muitos assuntos e aspectos.

Desenvolvimento, Inteligência de negócio (esta me acompanha por mais de 15 anos), ERPs Oracle e SAP, Qualidade e processos, CMMI, ITSM, BCM, Lean Six Sigma... enfim, muitas siglas, naturezas distintas, mas o aspecto mais importante: todas as mudanças foram bem vindas, e acrescentaram um pouco mais.

A implantação de métodos ágeis na gestão de um órgão de Governo, estudos com data science+R na área de saúde, participação da concepção de um dos maiores processos licitatórios de serviços do Estado da Bahia em anos recentes, e a gestão e fiscalização de um dos maiores BPOs decorrentes da contratação bem sucedida deste processo, marcaram minha volta ao Nordeste, após passar 11 anos em RJ, SP e ES. Um retorno com uma das melhores equipes com as quais já trabalhei, também no governo do Estado, onde comecei minha carreira.

Hoje tenho a chance de participar do processo de transformação digital de uma grande instituição de ensino superior, com unidades em todo o estado da Bahia, atuando juntamente com a diretoria de tecnologia e estratégia na definição de melhores praticas, objetivos e ferramentas para alcançar a excelência e domínio neste mercado dominado por grandes concorrentes internacionais. Atuei como coordenador, e depois como gerente, em todos os segmentos dentro da vertical de tecnologia: projetos, sistemas, infraestrutura e telecom, dados, digital, Customer Relationship... Mudanças, sempre, e o gosto de trabalhar com pessoas e encontrar soluções.

Sou bilíngue, inglês fluente, me envie uma mensagem, saiba mais sobre meu Curriculum Vitae recente por aqui e por que não, melhor ainda, vamos bater um papo, podemos conversar com mais detalhes sobre como essa caminhada foi feita, e o que me trouxe ao lugar onde estou, grande abraço!

# **Experience**



## Infrastructure and Technology Manager

UniFTC

Nov 2020 - Present (2 years 3 months)

Product Owner and Project Manager for the Infrastructure, Telecom and Hardware Support teams, including service management for cloud hosting, voice solutions, data provision, and digital related projects.

#### Main projects:

- Service modeling and implementation for hardware support in every business unit in the institution, replacing direct human resources contracts for a business partner. The service level was kept with a R\$ 700.000,00 budget reduction per year in costs.
- Voice and Datalink solutions optimization, across every business unity, with an estimated 90% reduction in costs (R\$ 580.000,00 per year).
- Customer Service Chat and Chatbot implementation, in partnership with Rocketchat/Weni, with a AQT of 1:30 minutes, and AST of 10:00, including academic and financial services for students, in and out of enrollment periods.
- Hubspot Market and Sales pilot project implementation, with two business units under scope, set for a total of 50 active operator in multiple channels, and a 300.000 contacts intake, rolled during second half of 2022.



#### Projetcs and Systems Supervisor/Manager

**UniFTC** 

Apr 2019 - Nov 2020 (1 year 8 months)

IT Solution Architecture as

- Project Manager and Scrum Master (Salvador BA, from apr/19 to dec/19) Reestablishment of Scrum Model for the development team, and management for the following projects:
- CRM to/from Core Academic Applications integration.
- Corporate DW Academic and commercial scopes.
- Classes enrollment optimization, resulting in a 7% teacher payroll reduction per year.
- Lean project for the enrollment process, resulting in a 85% reduction in time spent by the student to finish the procedures.
- Systems Supervisor (promoted to Manager in 2020) and Product Owner (Salvador BA, from dec/19 to nov/2020) Dev team management, including front-office core applications (business end academic Lyceum) and back-office (Prother ERP). Agile model solution architect for operations, Jira platform, and direct management of more then 25 projects from the portfolio for 2020, regarding the institution digital transformation. Also responsible for:
- Mass Implementation of remote classes with Learning Management System (Blackboard), within the first week of official lockdown in march/19.
- LGPD IT governance and policies definition.
- IT Budget modeling and proposal.
- Member of Strategic Planning committee along top institution leadership (President and VPs).



#### IT Supervisor

SAEB/Plansery - PRODEB

Aug 2016 - Mar 2019 (2 years 8 months)

ScrumMaster, with successful model running for both IT team (including Dev and Infrastructure) and a new implementation on the institution management group, where leaders for each business area acted as dev team, main manager acted as client and vice manager as P.O.. Backlog targeted mainly strategic subjects for the institution, both groups supported with Jira - from Atlassian.

#### Main accomplishments and projets:

- Definition of every aspect regarding IT, SLA, conformity testing and Business Continuity Planning for the institution greatest bidding, a Full BPO contract worth R\$ 397.674.786,00 over 60 months, executed in december 2017, promoted to full operation in march 2018.
- "R" DataScience projets, models and advanced reports:
- Linear predictive model over medical exams and procedures based on executed clinical appointments.
- Quantitative and Graphical analysis over patterns from providers revenues, including bills cumulative building.
- Providers profile building through data munging and Oracle Data base integration.
- Quantities versus Value, a net growth analysis to evaluate the institution fluctuation in costs.
- "R" main packages used in projects: Tidyverse, GGplot2, ROracle, DBI, QCC, Imtest, Orcutt e HoRM (linear model adjustments);
- Business Intelligence Database design over the institution core application (TOP Saúde) with Oracle and PowerBI, including data from medical bills and approvals/authorizationsbetweend 2014 and 2018, largely applied as main source of information for the BPO contract bidding.
- · Main Scrum extracts from Jira:
- IT team: 15 epics, 342 successfully completed stories in 26 sprints.
- Planserv Main Manegement Group: 13 epics, 247 successfully completed stories in 29 sprints.
- Designed and implemented Applications : Planserv Service desk, Evolutive Backlog System, E-Protocol.

### Senior Consultant

#### Accenture

May 2011 - Jul 2016 (5 years 3 months)

- Health & Public Services Support Lead (São Paulo SP) ScrumMaster/Product Owner for the continuous improvement and SQA Team, for every acting project in Brazil, supported by Rational Team Concert. Multi skilled active teams in three different states: SP, RJ and PE and interaction with global normative teams in Europe, between November 2015 and April 2016.
- BCM Lead (São Paulo SP) Team management for support and creation of over 230 Business Continuity Plans, across every active project in Brazil. Responsible for a new documentation concept, applied to EALA (Europe, Africa and Latin America) scope, which allowed 100% of coverage in Brazil in July 2016, regarding BCP.
- ITSM Project Leader and Specialist (Vitória ES) Vale Support Center service management implementation, with Remedy-BMC, global scope, executed by Accenture. Foundation Data and CMDB/ Config. Lead, acting in both project waves, including setup execution.
- SQA Specialist and Lead (Vitória ES) Accenture local SQA lead, CMMI based with project for major clients as Vale, Fleury and B2W.
- On-site BW/MDM Lead (Vitória ES) Liaison between Accenture Dev teams and Vale IT production management for SAP BW and MDM modules. Communication, prioritizing, conflict resolution, including client, suppliers, main teams and leadership.
- Business Intelligence Senior Consultant (Vitória ES) Informatica-Power Center specialist an team leader.

# PARTNERS

#### **Business Intelligence Consultant and Tech Lead**

#### Netpartners

Apr 2010 - Apr 2011 (1 year 1 month)

- Solution Architect

- Database design and modeling
- KPI definitions and implementation



#### **Oracle EBS Consultant**

#### Capgemini

Jan 2008 - Dec 2009 (2 years)

- GL assisted operation
- Custom reporting definition and implementation with Oracle B.I. Solutions
- DB Development



# Business Intelligence Specialist

Stefanini Brasil

Oct 2005 - Dec 2007 (2 years 3 months)

- Legacy B.I. solutions assisted operation and rollouts
- Project lead for 3 additional multi-dimentional models
- On-site support for major business key users



#### Senior Consultant and Business Intelligence Specialist

#### Sysdesign Consultoria

Jun 2000 - Sep 2005 (5 years 4 months)

- Technology vertical: Research and development with new tools
- Sales vertical: Proof of concept design and demonstrations, working closely with comercial team
- Project and Consultant vertical: Tech lead, responsible for every B.I. implementation across multipleclients and teams

#### Development Team Lead

Secretaria de Educação do Estado da Bahia

Mar 1997 - May 2000 (3 years 3 months)

- Development team leader
- Database modeling
- Database administration

## **Education**



#### Ruy Barbosa DeVry

Tecnólogo em Processamento de Dados, Tecnologia da Informação 1994 - 1998

#### IF FUCAPE Business School

Mestrado, Administração e Negócios Apr 2008 - Sep 2009 Incomplete, full credits but pending research

#### **Licenses & Certifications**

# Certified ScrumMaster (CSM)

Lean Six Sigma Green Belt

# **Skills**

Team Leadership • Strategy Alignment • Digital Transformation • Scrum • Data Science • Business Strategy • Software Quality Assurance • Customer Relationship Management (CRM) • Solution Architecture • Team Management